<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails&nbsp;4.2 | @vishnuatrai]]></title>
  <link href="http://vishnuatrai.in/blog/categories/rails-4-dot-2/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vishnuatrai.in/"/>
  <updated>2019-10-01T10:05:49+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://vishnuatrai.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[vishnuatrai.in]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[vishnu.atrai@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Is New in Rails 4.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://vishnuatrai.in/blog/2015/01/15/what-is-new-in-rails-4-dot-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T17:58:43+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://vishnuatrai.in/blog/2015/01/15/what-is-new-in-rails-4-dot-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Active Job</h3>

<p>Active Job is a framework for declaring jobs and making them run on a variety of queueing backends. These jobs can be everything from regularly scheduled clean-ups, to billing charges, to mailings. Anything that can be chopped up into small units of work and run in parallel.<!--more--></p>

<pre><code>class GuestsCleanupJob &lt; ActiveJob::Base
  queue_as :default

  def perform(*guests)
    # Do something later
  end
end

# Enqueue a job to be performed as soon the queuing system is free.
GuestsCleanupJob.perform_later guest

#Setting the Backend
# config/application.rb
module YourApp
  class Application &lt; Rails::Application
    # Be sure to have the adapter's gem in your Gemfile and follow
    # the adapter's specific installation and deployment instructions.
    config.active_job.queue_adapter = :sidekiq
  end
end
</code></pre>

<h3>Asynchronous Mails</h3>

<p>Building on top of Active Job, Action Mailer now comes with a <code>deliver_later</code> method that sends emails via the queue, so it doesn&rsquo;t block the controller or model if the queue is asynchronous (the default inline queue blocks).</p>

<p>Sending emails right away is still possible with <code>deliver_now</code>.</p>

<h3>Adequate Record</h3>

<p>Adequate Record is a set of performance improvements in Active Record that makes common find and find_by calls and some association queries up to 2x faster.</p>

<p>It works by caching common SQL queries as prepared statements and reusing them on similar calls, skipping most of the query-generation work on subsequent calls.</p>

<pre><code>Post.find(1)  # First call generates and cache the prepared statement
Post.find(2)  # Subsequent calls reuse the cached prepared statement

Post.find_by_title('first post')
Post.find_by_title('second post')

Post.find_by(title: 'first post')
Post.find_by(title: 'second post')

post.comments
post.comments(true)
</code></pre>

<p>Caching is not used in the following scenarios:</p>

<pre><code>- The model has a default scope
- The model uses single table inheritance
- find with a list of ids, eg.
    Post.find(1, 2, 3)
    Post.find([1,2])
- find_by with SQL fragments, eg.
    Post.find_by('published_at &lt; ?', 2.weeks.ago)
</code></pre>

<h3>Web Console</h3>

<p>Web Console adds an interactive Ruby console on every error page and provides a console view and controller helpers.</p>

<p>The interactive console on error pages lets you execute code in the context of the place where the exception originated. The console helper, if called anywhere in a view or controller, launches an interactive console with the final context, once rendering has completed.</p>

<h3>Foreign Key Support</h3>

<p>The migration DSL now supports adding and removing foreign keys. They are dumped to <code>schema.rb</code> as well. At this time, only the <code>mysql</code>, <code>mysql2</code> and <code>postgresql</code> adapters support foreign keys.</p>

<pre><code># add a foreign key to `articles.author_id` referencing `authors.id`
add_foreign_key :articles, :authors

# add a foreign key to `articles.author_id` referencing `users.lng_id`
add_foreign_key :articles, :users, column: :author_id, primary_key: "lng_id"

# remove the foreign key on `accounts.branch_id`
remove_foreign_key :accounts, :branches

# remove the foreign key on `accounts.owner_id`
remove_foreign_key :accounts, column: :owner_id
</code></pre>

<h3>References</h3>

<p><a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/4_2_release_notes.html">http://guides.rubyonrails.org/4_2_release_notes.html</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
